<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode
    xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.12"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.12
      http://knime.org/node/v2.12.xsd"
    icon="./excelformreader.png"
    type="Source">

  <name>Excel Reader (non-tabular)</name>

  <shortDescription>
    Reads non-tabular, form-structured Excel worksheets into a
    KNIME data table using a configurable field mapping definition.
  </shortDescription>

  <fullDescription>
    <intro>
      Reads one or more .xlsx files containing form-structured
      (non-tabular) worksheets and extracts field values into a
      standard KNIME data table. The form structure is defined
      by a connected input table that maps field names to Excel
      cell addresses (e.g. C4, B10:D15). Each worksheet produces
      one output row in wide mode, or one row per field in long mode.
      Supports single file, all sheets in a workbook, folder, and
      recursive folder reading modes.
    </intro>

    <option name="Reading Mode">
      Select Single File to read from one .xlsx file, or Folder
      to read all .xlsx files in a directory.
    </option>

    <option name="File / Folder Path">
      The path to the .xlsx file or the folder containing .xlsx files
      to be read.
    </option>

    <option name="Include Subfolders">
      When reading in Folder mode, also scan all subfolders
      recursively for .xlsx files.
    </option>

    <option name="Default Sheet Name">
      The name of the worksheet to read from each workbook. Leave
      blank to read the first sheet.
    </option>

    <option name="Excluded Sheet Names">
      Comma-separated list of worksheet names to skip when reading
      all sheets from a workbook. Default: Config.
    </option>

    <option name="Output Format">
      Wide: produces one row per form instance (file/sheet pair),
      with one column per field defined in the mapping table.
      Long: produces one row per field per form instance, with
      fixed columns field_name and value.
    </option>

    <option name="Add Source File and Sheet Name Columns">
      When enabled, adds source_file and sheet_name as the first
      two columns in the output table, identifying the origin of
      each row.
    </option>

    <option name="Range Cell Delimiter">
      When a Cell Range address specifies a range (e.g. B10:D15),
      all cell values in the range are concatenated using this
      delimiter string.
    </option>

    <option name="Include label fields in port 0">
      When enabled, label fields (Content Type = "label" in the
      form definition table) are included in the main output table
      alongside data fields, preserving the definition table order.
      When disabled, only data fields appear in port 0.
    </option>

    <option name="Output label fields in port 1">
      When enabled, label fields are extracted and output to port 1
      as a separate table with fixed columns: Name, Cell Range, and
      Cell Content (the extracted value), plus optional provenance
      columns. When disabled, port 1 produces an empty table.
    </option>

    <option name="On Missing Cell">
      Warn and set missing value: if a cell address cannot be
      resolved, a missing value is written and a warning is logged.
      Fail: the node fails immediately on the first unresolvable cell.
    </option>

    <option name="On Unparseable Value">
      Warn and set missing value: if a cell value cannot be converted
      to the declared data type, a missing value is written and a
      warning is logged.
      Fail: the node fails immediately on the first conversion error.
    </option>
  </fullDescription>

  <ports>
    <inPort index="0" name="Form Definition">
      A table defining the form structure mapping field names to Excel
      cell addresses. Required columns: Name (String) — the output
      column name; Cell Range (String) — the Excel cell address
      (e.g. C4) or range (e.g. B10:D15). Optional columns:
      Content Type (String) — the field role, either "data" (default)
      or "label"; Data Type (String) — the expected value type, one
      of: string, int, double, date, boolean (defaults to string if
      absent or blank).
    </inPort>
    <outPort index="0" name="Extracted Data">
      The extracted form data as a flat KNIME table. When provenance
      columns are enabled, source_file (String) and sheet_name (String)
      are always the first two columns, identifying the origin of each
      row. In wide mode: one row per (file, sheet) pair, one column per
      field. In long mode: one row per (file, sheet, field) triple, with
      fixed columns field_name (String) and value (String).
    </outPort>
    <outPort index="1" name="Label Fields">
      Label field values extracted from the form. One row per label
      field per (file, sheet) pair. Columns: Source File (optional),
      Sheet Name (optional), Name, Cell Range, Cell Content. Only
      populated when "Output label fields in port 1" is enabled in
      the General tab. Empty table otherwise.
    </outPort>
  </ports>

</knimeNode>
