<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<knimeNode
    xmlns="http://knime.org/node/v2.12"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:schemaLocation="http://knime.org/node/v2.12
      http://knime.org/node/v2.12.xsd"
    icon="./excelformreader.png"
    type="Source">

  <name>Excel Reader (non-tabular)</name>

  <shortDescription>
    Reads non-tabular, form-structured Excel worksheets
    (.xlsx) into a KNIME data table using a configurable
    field mapping definition.
  </shortDescription>

  <fullDescription>
    <intro>
      Reads one or more .xlsx files containing
      form-structured (non-tabular) worksheets and
      extracts field values into a standard KNIME data
      table. The form structure is defined by a connected
      input table that maps field names to Excel cell
      addresses (e.g. C4, B10:D15).

      The form definition table requires two columns:
      Name (the output column name) and Cell Range (the
      Excel cell address or range). Two optional columns
      are supported: Content Type ("data" or "label",
      defaults to "data") and Data Type (string, int,
      double, date, or boolean, defaults to string).

      Each worksheet produces one output row in wide mode,
      or one row per field in long mode. Label fields
      (Content Type = "label") can optionally be included
      in port 0 and/or output separately to port 1.

      Supports single file, all sheets in a workbook,
      folder, and recursive folder reading modes.
    </intro>

    <tab name="General">
      <option name="Input — Single File / Folder">
        Select Single File to read from one .xlsx file.
        Select Folder to read all matching .xlsx files
        from a directory. Enables the corresponding
        tab page and disables the other.
      </option>
      <option name="Output format">
        Wide: produces one row per form instance
        (file/sheet pair), with one column per field
        defined in the mapping table.
        Long: produces one row per field per form
        instance, with fixed columns field_name and value.
      </option>
      <option name="Include source filename">
        When enabled, adds a Source File column as the
        first column in the output table, containing
        the absolute path of the source .xlsx file.
      </option>
      <option name="Include sheet name">
        When enabled, adds a Sheet Name column as the
        second column in the output table (after Source
        File if enabled), containing the worksheet name.
      </option>
      <option name="Include label fields in port 0">
        When enabled, fields with Content Type = "label"
        are included in the main output table (port 0)
        alongside data fields, preserving the definition
        table order. When disabled, only data fields
        appear in port 0.
      </option>
      <option name="Output label fields in port 1">
        When enabled, label fields are extracted and
        output to port 1 as a separate table with fixed
        columns: Name, Cell Range, and Cell Content (the
        extracted value), plus optional provenance
        columns. When disabled, port 1 produces an empty
        table.
      </option>
      <option name="Include format condition operator columns">
        When enabled, adds a Format Condition Operator
        column immediately after each field value column
        in wide mode, or as an additional fixed column in
        long mode and port 1. The column contains the
        conditional formatting rule operator(s) applied to
        the cell (e.g. BETWEEN, EQUAL, GT). Multiple
        operators are concatenated with the range
        delimiter. Missing value when no conditional
        formatting rule is applied to the cell.
      </option>
      <option name="Include validation type columns">
        When enabled, adds a Validation Type column
        immediately after each field value column (and
        after the Format Condition Operator column if
        enabled) in wide mode, or as an additional fixed
        column in long mode and port 1. The column
        contains the data validation type applied to the
        cell (e.g. LIST, INTEGER, DATE). Multiple types
        are concatenated with the range delimiter. Missing
        value when no data validation rule is applied to
        the cell.
      </option>
      <option name="On missing cell">
        Warn and insert missing value: if a cell address
        cannot be resolved, a missing value is written
        and a warning is logged. Fail: the node fails
        immediately on the first unresolvable cell.
      </option>
      <option name="On unparseable value">
        Warn and insert missing value: if a cell value
        cannot be converted to the declared Data Type,
        a missing value is written and a warning is
        logged. Fail: the node fails immediately on the
        first conversion error.
      </option>
    </tab>

    <tab name="File">
      <option name="Read from">
        The file system to read from. Currently only
        Local File System is supported. Additional file
        systems (mountpoint, relative to) may be added
        in a future release.
      </option>
      <option name="File">
        The path to the .xlsx file to read. Use the
        Browse button to open a file chooser filtered
        to .xlsx files.
      </option>
      <option name="Process single sheet">
        Read exactly one worksheet from the selected
        file using one of three selection methods:
        First (the first non-hidden sheet with data),
        By name (select from a dropdown of available
        sheets), or By position (0-based index).
      </option>
      <option name="Include hidden worksheets (single)">
        When enabled, hidden worksheets are included
        when determining the first sheet or populating
        the By name dropdown. When disabled, hidden
        sheets are excluded.
      </option>
      <option name="Process many sheets">
        Read all matching worksheets from the selected
        file. Use All to include every sheet, Blacklist
        to exclude named sheets, or Whitelist to include
        only named sheets. Sheet names are
        comma-separated and matched case-insensitively.
      </option>
      <option name="Include hidden worksheets (many)">
        When enabled, hidden worksheets are included
        when processing many sheets. When disabled,
        hidden sheets are skipped.
      </option>
    </tab>

    <tab name="Folder">
      <option name="Read from">
        The file system to read from. Currently only
        Local File System is supported.
      </option>
      <option name="Folder">
        The path to the folder containing .xlsx files
        to read. Use the Browse button to open a
        folder chooser.
      </option>
      <option name="Include subfolders">
        When enabled, .xlsx files in all subfolders
        are also included recursively.
      </option>
      <option name="Include hidden folders">
        When enabled, hidden subfolders are included
        during recursive scanning. Only available when
        Include subfolders is checked.
      </option>
      <option name="Filter by file extension">
        When enabled, only files matching the specified
        extensions (comma-separated, default: xlsx) are
        included. When disabled, all files in the folder
        are considered.
      </option>
      <option name="Include hidden files">
        When enabled, hidden files are included in the
        folder scan.
      </option>
      <option name="Process single sheet">
        Read exactly one worksheet from each file using
        First, By name (text input), or By position
        (0-based index).
      </option>
      <option name="Include hidden worksheets (single)">
        When enabled, hidden worksheets are considered
        when selecting the sheet per file.
      </option>
      <option name="Process many sheets">
        Read all matching worksheets from each file.
        Use All, Blacklist, or Whitelist with
        comma-separated sheet names.
      </option>
      <option name="Include hidden worksheets (many)">
        When enabled, hidden worksheets are included
        when processing many sheets per file.
      </option>
    </tab>
  </fullDescription>

  <ports>
    <inPort index="0" name="Form Definition">
      A table defining the form structure mapping field
      names to Excel cell addresses. Required columns:
      Name (String) — the output column name; Cell Range
      (String) — the Excel cell address (e.g. C4) or
      range (e.g. B10:D15). Optional columns: Content
      Type (String) — the field role, either "data"
      (default) or "label"; Data Type (String) — the
      expected value type, one of: string, int, double,
      date, boolean (defaults to string if absent or
      blank).
    </inPort>
    <outPort index="0" name="Extracted Data">
      The extracted form data as a flat KNIME table.
      When provenance columns are enabled, Source File
      and Sheet Name are the first columns. In wide
      mode: one row per (file, sheet) pair, one column
      per field. In long mode: one row per (file, sheet,
      field) triple, with fixed columns field_name and
      value. Label fields are included when the
      corresponding toggle is enabled in the General tab.
      When format condition operator or validation type
      columns are enabled, additional columns are appended
      per field in wide mode, or as fixed columns in long
      mode.
    </outPort>
    <outPort index="1" name="Label Fields">
      Label field values extracted from the form. One
      row per label field per (file, sheet) pair.
      Fixed columns: Source File (optional), Sheet Name
      (optional), Name, Cell Range, Cell Content.
      Empty table when "Output label fields in port 1"
      is disabled in the General tab. When format
      condition operator or validation type columns are
      enabled, they appear as additional fixed columns
      after Cell Content.
    </outPort>
  </ports>

</knimeNode>
